Konrad and Florence Ballin Cramer
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
- Christmas Card Album, 1921-1931, 1940, 1961, undated, Series 3:; (Box 3; 0.8 linear feet)
  - Christmas Card Album, 1921-1931, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Items Found In Christmas Card Album, 1926, 1931, 1940, 1961, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Writings, 1897-1962, undated, Series 4:; (Boxes 4-5, 11; 1.7 linear feet)
  This series includes the notes and writings of Florence Ballin Cramer and Konrad Cramer, along with scattered notes and writings by others. Types of material include an address book; appointment books; diaries, notes and excerpts from diaries, and items found in diaries; essays; notebooks; poems; a movie scenario; and notes. Some of the notebooks include drafts of outgoing correspondence.
  Diaries include twelve volumes kept by Konrad Cramer from 1945 to 1962, and two volumes and some loose pages by Florence Ballin Cramer, as well as notes and excerpts from diaries that are not part of the collection. Konrad Cramer's diary entries are sporadic, recording his farming activities, weather conditions, and personal activities. The volume for 1949 also contains notes from Florence Ballin Cramer's lengthy hospital stay and his contacts in New York during that time. Florence Ballin Cramer's diaries date from her school days and travels to Europe, when she met Konrad Cramer, and contain many sketches. A later volume documents her hospital stay, and also contains sketches. Also found are detailed notes and excerpts from diaries not found in the collection, possibly loaned for microfilming and returned to the Cramers. In addition, loose items removed from several diaries, including those found within the collection and those removed from the collection, are filed here and include photographs of Florence, unidentified friends, a costume ball, and the area around Woodstock; early exhibition documentation; clippings; a sketch; and writings by Florence and Irving Ballin.
  Konrad Cramer's essays mostly concern technical aspects of painting, drawing, printmaking, and photography, with a few essays on broad concepts such as modernism and design. Also found are numerous drafts of informal essays about people known to Cramer, including people from the Woodstock community such as Hervey White, founder of the Maverick artist's colony. Florence Ballin Cramer's essays include a lengthy autobiographical essay about her earliest visits to Woodstock as a student of the Art Student's League summer classes, essays on Ameican crafts and Mexican artists, and other subjects.
  Konrad Cramer's earliest notebook contains recipes gathered from his peers for paints and varnishes. Other notebooks contain essays, technical notes, drafts of outgoing letters, and some notes from meetings of Woodstock organizations. Volumes given titles by Cramer are listed by title, and titled essays within volumes are noted in the folder contents list. Florence Ballin Cramer's notebooks include two volumes from her adolescence containing notes and drawings.
  Notes include travel notes and an annotated map from a 1938 trip West and notes written by Florence Ballin Cramer and Konrad Cramer including technical photo notes, recipes, quotes from published sources, contact information, and other miscellany. Collection notes, probably written by Florence Ballin Cramer, describe materials in the Cramer papers that have become separated from the items they describe. Miscellaneous notes include a student's poem, a list of books about Greenwich Village, and a brief note from a friend.
  Additional notes and writings are found in Biographical Materials and Personal Business Records. Picture books by the Cramers are found in Artwork.
  Most of the papers in this series were previously microfilmed on reels 2753-2755, unless otherwise noted in the folder heading.
  - Address Book, Florence Ballin Cramer, circa 1910s (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Appointment Books, Florence Ballin (Cramer), 1908, 1910 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Diaries (Box 4)
    - Konrad Cramer, 1945-1950, 1957-1962, (12 volumes in 11 folders) (Box 4, Folder 3-13)
    - Florence Ballin Cramer (Box 4)
      - 1911, undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
      - 1949-1951 (Box 4, Folder 15)
      - Notes (1906-1907, 1926-1943), undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
      - Excerpts from Removed Diaries, 1916-1917, 1934, 1955, 1958-1962 (Box 4, Folder 17)
      - Loose Items Removed from 1908-1910 Diary, 1907-1913, undated (Box 4, Folder 18)
      - Items Removed from 1911 Diary, 1940, undated (Box 4, Folder 19)
      - Excerpts and Items Removed from Unspecified Diary, 1909, 1917, 1920, 1925, 1935, undated (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Essays (Box 5)
    - Konrad Cramer (Box 5)
      - "The Painter's Handbook", 1932 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - "The Good Painter's Handbook", 1933 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      - "The Artist in the Darkroom", circa 1937 (Box 5, Folder 3)
      - "The Tools for Drawing", undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
      - "The Artist and His Craft", undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
        (Includes sections by unidentified authors)
      - "How to Display the Modern Photograph", undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
      - "Modern Tendencies in Art", undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
      - "The Origin of Design", undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
      - "The What and How of Photography", undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
      - "The Why and How of the Art Department", undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
      - "Memo for the Art Room" (Dalton School), undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
      - People and Woodstock History, 1937-1962, undated, (see also OV 11) (Box 5, Folder 12)
        (Amalie Cramer; Harold Reynolds; Hervey White and the Maverick Story; Rosie Magee; J. Albert of Munich and Albertypes; Sidney Berkowitz; Carl Olaf Eric Lindin)
      - Miscellaneous Essays and Notes about Art, 1934, 1960, undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
      - Miscellaneous Essays, Non-Art Subjects, 1957-1958, undated (Box 5, Folder 14)
      - (Copies), 1953, undated (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Florence Ballin Cramer (Box 5)
      - Autobiographical Sketch about Woodstock circa 1906-1910, undated (Box 5, Folder 16)
      - "The Artists in Mexico", undated (Box 5, Folder 17)
      - "Craftwork In America", circa 1928-1931 (Box 5, Folder 18)
      - Miscellaneous Non-Art Subjects, 1938, 1950, 1959, undated (Box 5, Folder 19)
      - (Copies), undated (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Unknown Author, "The Kindergarten - What It Is", undated (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Notebooks (Box 5)
    - Konrad Cramer (see also Artwork, sketchbook with notes on printmaking) (Box 5)
      - 1929-1930 (Box 5, Folder 22)
        (Contains recipes from various artists for paint, varnish, and other media; and technical notes)
      - 1944-1945 (Box 5, Folder 23)
        (Contains the essay "A Practical Handbook of Drawing", with editor's comments)
      - "Handbook of Drawing, Volume 1", 1945 (Box 5, Folder 24)
        (Also contains drafts of outgoing letters)
      - "Volume 2", 1945, (2 folders) (Box 5, Folder 25-26)
        (Contains "Handbook of Drawing, Volume 2")
      - "Notes on Stieglitz", 1946 (Box 5, Folder 27)
        (Also contains meeting notes of the Woodstock Foundation, and an essay about Thanksgiving at Rivington Hospital)
      - 1957 (Box 5, Folder 28)
        (Contains the essay "Developing 35mm Film by Inspection," also drafts of outgoing letters and notes regarding the Kleinert Wing of the Woodstock Foundation)
      - 1952, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 29)
        (Contains drafts of outgoing letters and technical notes)
      - circa 1958 (Box 5, Folder 30)
        (Contains fragment of essay "Restoring Oil Paintings" and drafts of outgoing letters)
      - "Notes on Lectures for Painting Materials", undated (Box 5, Folder 31)
      - undated (Box 5, Folder 32)
        (Contains essays related to photography and notes on Mozart's letters)
    - Florence Ballin Cramer (Box 5)
      - 1897-1898, (2 volumes in 2 folders) (Box 5, Folder 33-34)
    - Unknown Author (Box 5)
      - Recipes in German, 1800s (Box 5, Folder 35)
      - Forecast of Futures of Woodstock Children, 1935 (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Poetry (Box 5)
    - Florence Ballin Cramer (Box 5)
      - 1924-1929, undated (Box 5, Folder 37)
      - Poems for Children, 1920s (Box 5, Folder 38)
    - Irving Ballin, 1908-1912 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Movie Scenario by Konrad and Florence Ballin Cramer, circa 1912, 1938 (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - Notes (Box 5)
    - Travel Notes and Map (see also Reel 2756), 1938, undated (Box 5, Folder 41)
    - Miscellaneous Notes by Konrad and Florence Ballin Cramer, undated (Box 5, Folder 42)
    - Notes by Manuel Komroff, undated (Box 5, Folder 43)
    - Notes from Oral Histories of the Cramers and Hermine Kleinert by Sam Eskin, 1962, undated (Box 5, Folder 44)
    - Collection Notes (not microfilmed), 1958-1959, undated (Box 5, Folder 45)
    - Excerpts from Correspondence (1937), undated (Box 5, Folder 46)
    - Contacts, undated (Box 5, Folder 47)
    - Miscellaneous Notes, undated (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - Oversized Writings, (See Box 5, f12) (Box 11 (OV))
- Personal Business Records, 1918-1962, undated, Series 5:; (Boxes 5, 10; 0.3 linear feet)
  This series contains records of Florence Ballin Cramer's and Konrad Cramer's respective artistic careers, other business and civic pursuits, and personal finances.
  Artwork and exhibit records of Konrad Cramer include correspondence with the Dudensing Gallery, the Whitney Museum, John Graham and Sons, the Woodstock Artists Association and other exhibitors and dealers. Also found are receipts and price lists, some of which are illustrated with rough sketches. Florence Ballin Cramer's artwork and exhibit records include price lists, receipts, a guest book, and mailing lists, most of which refer to her 1953 exhibition at the Woodstock Town House gallery. Documents from her exhibitions at the Marie Harriman Gallery and Long Island University are also found. Additional materials related to exhibitions can be found in Printed Materials.
  Records of the Florence Ballin Cramer's 57th Street gallery, the Florence Gallery, include photographs of Florence in the gallery, her contract with H. Kevorkian for the use of the space, clippings, catalogs, price lists, and letters from artists and subscribers to the gallery, including Andrew Dasburg, Gene Speicher, Stefan Hirsch, Elie Nadelman, Christine Chaplin, Paul Rohland, Caroline Speare, John Everts Bates, and Forbes Watson. Also found are drafts of letters and other writings by Florence promoting the gallery and its mission, and a small card file recording sales, income and expenses, and contact information.
  Records of Florence Cramer's shop in Woodstock consist mostly of accounting and inventory records. Correspondence related to this venture can be found in the correspondence series, especially for the years 1925 to 1927.
  Records of Woodstock craft organizations include legal contracts, by-laws, letters, notes, press releases, and other records related to the Woodstock Guild of Craftsmen and the Crafts' Foundation of Woodstock. Included are drafts of letters and speeches related to the opening of the Kleinert Wing of the Woodstock Guild of Craftsmen's building in 1958. See Correspondence, Writings, and Printed Materials for additional materials related to these groups.
  Konrad Cramer's employment contracts with the Children's University School (now the Dalton School) and an advertising firm are also found. For materials related to his various teaching endeavors, see Writings and Printed Materials.
  Materials in this series were previously scattered among the various accessions. Microfilm reels on which most of the documents in this series can be viewed are indicated in parentheses by the folder heading. Researchers should note that the order of documents on microfilm does not reflect the current physical arrangement.
  - Artwork and Exhibit Records (Box 5)
    - Konrad Cramer (Reels D170-D171, 2755), 1929-1936, 1952-1962, undated, (4 folders) (Box 5, Folder 49-52)
    - Florence Ballin Cramer (Reels D171, 2755), 1933, 1936, 1953, 1957, undated, (See also OV 10) (Box 5, Folder 53)
  - Art Students League By-Law Amendments (Reel D170), 1906 (Box 5, Folder 54)
  - Florence Gallery Records (Reel D170), 1918-1923, undated, (4 folders) (Box 5, Folder 55-58)
  - Florence Ballin Cramer's Woodstock Shop Records (Reel 2755), 1922-1944, undated, (3 folders) (Box 5, Folder 59-61)
  - Records of Woodstock Craft Organizations (Reel 2755 and 2756), 1948-1959, undated, (2 folders; see also OV 10) (Box 5, Folder 62-63)
  - Records of Other Woodstock Organizations (Reel 2757), undated (Box 5, Folder 64)
    (Woodstock Town House, Maverick Summer Concerts)
  - Konrad Cramer Patent on Camera Accessory (Reel 2755), 1939 (Box 5, Folder 65)
  - Konrad Cramer's Employment Contracts (Reel 2755), 1926, 1929 (Box 5, Folder 66)
  - Personal Financial Records (Box 5)
    - Account Books (Reel 2755), 1955-1959, (2 folders) (Box 5, Folder 67-68)
      (Contain sketches)
    - Assets (Reel 2755), 1928, 1930, 1954-1960 (Box 5, Folder 69)
    - Bank and Stock Records (Reel 2755 and unfilmed), 1932, 1955-1962, undated (Box 5, Folder 70)
    - Bills and Receipts (Reel 2755 and unfilmed), 1919-1961, undated (Box 5, Folder 71)
    - Property Improvements (Reel 2755), 1924, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 72)
  - Oversized Personal Business Records (See Box 5, f53 and 62) (Box 10 (OV))
- Printed Materials, 1906-1968, undated, Series 6:; (Boxes 6-7, 9, 11; 1.8 linear feet)
  This series includes clippings, exhibition catalogs, press releases, printed ephemera related to Woodstock organizations and events, and over a dozen periodicals and books by and about Woodstock artists and writers. Other materials include letterhead, business cards, brochures, posters, maps, postcards, and other publicity pieces.
  Exhibition announcements, catalogs, and invitations are for Florence Ballin Cramer's and Konrad Cramer's group and solo shows as well as shows of other artists. Clippings are mostly from New York City and Woodstock-area papers and include notices and reviews of exhibitions, art news and features, articles about friends and neighbors, and other miscellany. Some clippings have been pasted to other types of documents, such as contracts or correspondence related to one of the Cramers' exhibitions, and appear to have been cut from a scrapbook. A number of newspapers saved in their entirety feature coverage of significant local events in Woodstock.
  Brochures and letterhead are found for Konrad and Florence Ballin Cramer's various professional endeavors, including the Konrad Cramer's School for Miniature Photography as well as his auto mechanic service, Florence Ballin Cramer's antique shop, and other entities, many of which appear to be made with a manual letter-press and decorated with relief prints. Prints by other artists are filed separately and include a large engraved map of Woodstock created by Marg and Rudolph Wetterau. Additional prints are found in the Artwork series.
  Woodstock organizations and events are documented here with brochures, posters, announcements, catalogs, programs, directories, and newsletters, many of which refer to Konrad or Florence Ballin Cramer's involvement in the organization. Woodstock publications include thirteen titles of books, little magazines, and journals featuring prints, drawings, stencils, and writings of the Cramers and other Woodstock-area artists and writers such as Hervey White, Paul Rohland, Peggy Bacon, Alexander Brook, John Carroll, Andrew Dasburg, John Evert Bates, Jean Paul Slusser, Grace Mott Johnson, Judson Smith, Rudolph and Marg Wetterau, Arnold Blanch, and many others. The largest run in the series is for the satirical arts paper Hue and Cry, which includes several complete volumes for its early years as well as two annuals with original relief prints on rice paper and many art reproductions. Issues of both The Wasp and The Overlook contain lengthy essays about Konrad Cramer. Woodstock Gargoyles features articles by many mainstays of the Woodstock community including Konrad Cramer, and is the first and only issue of that publication.
  Additional scattered printed materials are filed with Biographical Materials, Correspondence, Writings (Items found in diaries), and Personal Business Records. See series descriptions for more details.
  Printed materials in this series were part of two separate accessions previously arranged and microfilmed on reels D171 and 2755-2757, unless otherwise noted.
  - Exhibition Announcements, Catalogs, and Invitations, 1909-1968, undated, (8 folders) (Box 6, Folder 1-8)
  - Clippings, 1908-1962, 1965, undated, (13 folders) (Box 6, Folder 9-21)
  - Magazines, Journals, and Other Articles, 1906-1958, undated, (3 folders) (Box 6, Folder 22-24)
  - Newspapers (not microfilmed), 1925-1955, (3 folders) (Box 6, Folder 25-27)
  - Press Releases and Advertisements, 1951-1962 (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Reproductions of Artwork, 1937, undated (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - Business Cards, 1920, undated (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - Cramers' Brochures and Letterhead, undated (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - Woodstock Organizations and Events (Box 6)
    - Woodstock Artists Association, 1933, 1947-1948, undated (Box 6, Folder 32)
    - Woodstock Guild of Craftsmen, 1948-1951 (Box 6, Folder 33)
    - Woodstock School of Painting, 1920, 1934-1935 (Box 6, Folder 34)
    - Woodstock School of Miniature Photography, 1937-1946 (Box 6, Folder 35)
    - Miscellaneous Woodstock Schools and Workshops, 1952-1958, undated (Box 6, Folder 36)
    - "The First Art Film Festival in America", 1951 (Box 6, Folder 37)
    - The Woodstock Festival, 1959-1960, undated (Box 6, Folder 38)
    - Programs for Cultural Events in Woodstock, 1931-1960, undated, (see also OV 11) (Box 6, Folder 39)
    - Woodstock Civic Organizations, 1933-1959, undated (Box 6, Folder 40)
  - Woodstock Publications (Box 6)
    - The Plowshare, 1917-1919, (2 folders) (Box 6, Folder 41-42)
    - Woodstock, an Essay by Richard Le Gallienne, with Reproductions of Work by Woodstock Artists, 1923 (Box 6, Folder 43)
    - Woodstock Almanac, 1924 (Box 6, Folder 44)
    - The Maverick Hoot, 1927 (Box 6, Folder 45)
    - Hue and Cry, 1923-1926, 1929, 1933, 1945, (8 folders; see also Box 9, sol) (Box 7, Folder 1-8)
    - The Woodstock Bulletin, 1929-1930 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - The Overlook, 1931-1932, (2 folders) (Box 7, Folder 10-11)
    - Art Notes, Vol. 11, No. 10, 1932 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Publications of the Woodstock Historical Society, 1930-1939, (3 folders) (Box 7, Folder 13-15)
    - Fallen Leaves by Carl Eric Lindin, 1941 (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Woodstock Gargoyles, 1949 (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - The Wasp, 1952, 1954 (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - The Bulletin, 1960-1961 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Other Brochures, Mailings, and Posters (Box 7)
    - Art Students League, 1948-1950, undated, (See also OV 11) (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - Clubs, 1950, undated (Box 7, Folder 21)
      (United World Federalists, Circle of Confusion)
    - Camera Equipment, 1947-1958, undated (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - Mexico, 1934, undated (Box 7, Folder 23)
    - Miscellaneous Brochures and Mailings, 1947-1951, undated (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - Blank Cards and Postcards, undated (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - Relief Prints and Engravings Including Map of Woodstock (partially microfilmed), 1912, 1927, undated, (See also OV 11) (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - Oversized Issues of Hue and Cry (See Box 7, f1, 3-6, 8) (Box 9 (sol))
  - Oversized Programs for Cultural Events in Woodstock (See Box 6, f39) (Box 11 (OV))
  - Oversized Art Students League Posters (See Box 7, f20) (Box 11 (OV))
  - Oversized Relief Prints and Engravings Including Map of Woodstock (See Box 7, f26) (Box 11 (OV))
- Photographs, 1906-1960, undated, Series 7:; (Box 7; 0.5 linear feet)
  This series includes snapshots, photo postcards, fine prints, and negatives depicting Florence Ballin Cramer, Konrad Cramer, their friends, schools, studios, Woodstock parties, the Maverick Festival, scenic views of Woodstock, and photographs of works of art.
  A series of early photographs in the pictorialist style appear to have been made on printing-out paper and are filed under the heading "Early Woodstock Views and Figures." Their photographer is unknown, but the female figure depicted is most likely Florence Ballin. A few examples of photo experiments with color and collage, probably by Konrad Cramer, are also found. Photographs filed under the heading "Portraits of Friends" include formal portraits, snapshots, and a series of posed photographs Konrad Cramer took of friends with family members in their homes.
  Many of the photographs in this series were probably taken by Konrad and Florence Ballin Cramer, although many are uncredited. Wherever possible, photographs that appear to have been taken together have been filed together. Except for very early photographs, many of the individuals pictured have been identified on the photographs themselves, and names of those identified are noted in the folder listing.
  Additional photographs are found in Correspondence, Personal Business Records (Florence Gallery records), and Writings (Items found in diaries). Writings and notes related to Konrad Cramer's work with photography are found in the Writings series, and manuals for cameras are filed with Printed Materials.
  Except for photographs of works of art, which were not microfilmed, photographs in this series were microfilmed in an earlier arrangement on reels 1203 and 1204, unless otherwise noted.
  - Early Florence Ballin, Irving Ballin, and Friends, 1906, 1919, 1928, undated (Box 7, Folder 27)
    (Also pictured are Homer and Carlota Saint-Gaudens and Henry Lee McFee, with note from McFee)
  - Early Konrad Cramer and Friends (one image on Reel 2756), circa 1909, 1915 (Box 7, Folder 28)
  - Konrad Cramer's Studio, 1952, 1958, undated (Box 7, Folder 29)
  - Florence Ballin's Studio, circa 1900s (Box 7, Folder 30)
  - Florence Ballin Cramer and Konrad Cramer, 1930s-1951, undated (Box 7, Folder 31)
  - Florence Ballin Cramer's Exhibit Opening, Woodstock, circa 1950s (Box 7, Folder 32)
  - Portraits of Friends (Box 7)
    - 1908, 1923, undated (Box 7, Folder 33)
      (pictured are Carlota Saint-Gaudens, Louise Hellstrom, Henry Lee McFee (Reel 1817 and digitized), Arnold Blanch (Reel 439 and digitized), Karl Fortess, Carl Walters, Sara Kuniyoshi, Marion Greenwood, Barbara Shermund, John Striebel, John Carlson)
    - Gene and Elsie Speicher (One photo on Reel 440 and digitized), 1930s, undated, (4 folders, including duplicates and copy print) (Box 7, Folder 34-37)
    - Frank Chase and Son Dennis, circa 1930s (Box 7, Folder 38)
    - Neil Ives and Daughter Peggy Cole, 1930s (Box 7, Folder 39)
    - Henry Billings, undated (Box 7, Folder 40)
    - Hervey White, undated (Box 7, Folder 41)
    - Merril (Pixie) and Fritz Mueller, 1960 (Box 7, Folder 42)
    - Judson and Mary Smith, undated, (2 folders, including copy print) (Box 7, Folder 43-44)
    - Yasuo Kuniyoshi (One photo on Reel 439 and digitized), undated, (2 folders, including copy negative) (Box 7, Folder 45-46)
  - Art Classes, Group and Candid Shots, 1904-1909, undated, (2 folders, including copy negatives and prints) (Box 7, Folder 47-48)
    (includes Art Students League classes, picturing Edith Morrell, Remington Schuyler, R. Nisbet, John Carlson, Florence Ballin, Grace Johnson, Mollie Bannister, Mary Reilly, Pop Goltz, Birge Harrison, Andrew Dasburg, among others)
  - Maverick Festival, 1922, undated, (2 folders, including copy print) (Box 7, Folder 49-50)
    (pictured are Ernest Brace, Florence Ballin Cramer, Reeves Brace, Konrad Cramer, Helen Walters, Eugenie Gershoy, Harry Gottlieb, and Marjorie Barnes)
  - Woodstock People, circa 1909-1938, undated (Box 7, Folder 51)